  <file>
<page>
    <title>Autodesk Maya</title>
    <id>113014</id>
    <revision>
      <id>390328782</id>
      <timestamp>2010-10-12T17:44:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>The Thing That Should Not Be</username>
        <id>5026668</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor />
      <comment>[[WP:RBK|Reverted]] edits by [[Special:Contributions/168.221.159.15|168.221.159.15]] ([[User_talk:168.221.159.15|talk]]) to last revision by Avoided ([[WP:HG|HG]] [[User:TTTSNB/CustomHuggle|(Custom)]])</comment>
      <text xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=March 2008}}
{{Merge from|Autodesk toxik|date=December 2009}}
{{Infobox software|
 name = Autodesk Maya|
 logo=[[Image:Autodesk Maya.svg|135px]] |
 screenshot = [[Image:Autodesk Maya 2011 x64 Modeling a Lada.png|250px]]|
 caption = Autodesk Maya 2011 running on [[Windows 7]] using realtime CGFX shaders |
 developer = The [[Autodesk Media and Entertainment|Media and Entertainment Division]] of [[Autodesk]] |
 latest_release_version = 2011 (12.0) |
 latest_release_date = April 6th, 2010 |
 operating_system = [[Linux]], [[Mac OS X]], [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] |
 genre = [[3D computer graphics]] |
 commercial = yes |
 license = [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]] |
 website = [http://www.autodesk.com/maya www.autodesk.com/maya]}}
'''Autodesk Maya''' is a software application used for [[3D animation]], [[3D modeling]], simulation, visual effects, [[Rendering (computer graphics)|rendering]], [[match moving]], and [[compositing]]. It is developed in [[Toronto]] by [[Autodesk]]'s [[Autodesk Media and Entertainment|Media and Entertainment Division]] (formerly [[Alias Systems Corporation|Alias]]).

Maya is used in the [[film]] and [[television|TV industry]], as well as for [[Video game|computer and video games]], architectural visualization and design.

The product is named after [[Maya (illusion)|Maya]], the [[Sanskrit]] term for &quot;illusion.&quot;

==History==
{{See|Maya release history}}

Maya is the culmination of three 3D software lines: Wavefront's The Advanced Visualizer (in California), Thomson Digital Image (TDI) Explore (in France) and Alias' Power Animator (in Canada). In 1993 Wavefront purchased TDI, and in 1995 [[Silicon Graphics|Silicon Graphics Incorporated]] (SGI) purchased both Alias and Wavefront (due to pressure from [[Microsoft]]'s purchase of [[Softimage (company)|Softimage]] earlier that year) and combined them into one working company, producing a single package from their collective source code. The combined company was referred to as [[Alias Systems Corporation|Alias{{!}}Wavefront]]. In the mid-1990s, the most popular pipeline in Hollywood films was a combination of tools: Alias Studio for modeling, [[Softimage 3D|Softimage{{pipe}}3D]] for animation, and [[PhotoRealistic RenderMan]] for rendering.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://silicon-valley.siggraph.org/MeetingNotes/ILM.html |title=Jurassic Park - The Illusion of Life}}&lt;/ref&gt; This combination was used for numerous films, such as [[Jurassic Park (film)|Jurassic Park]], [[The Abyss]] and ''[[Terminator 2: Judgement Day]]''. It took Alias|Wavefront two more years after the merger to release Maya.

Both Alias and Wavefront were working on their next generation of software at the time of the merger. Alias had taken a Macintosh product, &quot;[[Alias Sketch|Alias Sketch!]]&quot;, moved it to the SGI platform and added many features to it. The code name for this project was Maya. Maya was developed in close collaboration with Walt Disney Feature Animation, during the production of ''[[Dinosaur (film)|Dinosaur]]'', and the GUI was all customizable as a requirement from Disney so they could set up their own GUI and workflow based on decades of animation experience. This had a large impact on the openness of Maya and later also helped the software become an industry standard, since many facilities implement extensive proprietary customization of the software to gain competitive advantage.

It was then decided to adopt Alias' &quot;Maya&quot; architecture, and merge Wavefront's code with it.

In the early days of development, Maya started with [[Scheme (programming language)|Scheme]], then moved to [[Tcl]] as the scripting language, in order to leverage its similarity to the Unix shell language. Sophia, the scripting language in Wavefront's [[Dynamation (software)|Dynamation]], was eventually chosen as the basis of MEL, and helped eased integration of other Wavefront technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= In silico: 3D animation and simulation of cell biology with Maya and MEL|last=Sharpe |first=  Jason Sharpe|coauthors=Charles J. Lumsden, Nicholas Woolridge |year= 2008|publisher=Morgan Kaufmann|  page=263|isbn= 0-1237-3655-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon its release in 1998, Alias|Wavefront discontinued all previous animation-based software lines including Alias Power Animator, encouraging consumers to upgrade to Maya. It succeeded in expanding its product line to take over a great deal of market share, with leading visual effects companies such as [[Industrial Light and Magic]] and [[Tippett Studio]] switching from [[Softimage]] to Maya for the animation software.

Later, Alias|Wavefront was renamed Alias. In 2003, Alias was sold by SGI to the [[Ontario Teachers' Pension Plan]] and the private equity investment firm [[Accel-KKR]]. In October 2005, Alias was sold again, this time to [[Autodesk]], and on January 10, 2006, Autodesk completed the acquisition and ''Alias'' Maya is now known as '''Autodesk Maya'''.

In 2003, Maya won an Academy Award &quot;for scientific and technical achievement&quot;, citing use &quot;on nearly every feature using 3-D computer-generated images.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Scientific and Technical Achievements Honored with Academy Awards|url=http://www.oscars.org/press/pressreleases/2003/03.01.06.html|date=2003-01-06|accessdate=2009-10-01}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Release history==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Version !! Build number !! Date
|-
| Maya 8.0
| 8.0
| August 2006
|-
| Maya 8.5
| 8.5
| 15 January 2007
|-
| Maya 2008
| 9.0
| September 2007
|-
| Maya 2009
| 10.0
| August 2008
|-
| Maya 2010
| 11.0
| August 2009
|-
| Maya 2011
| 12.0
| 6 April 2010
|}

==Overview==
[[Image:Autodesk Maya 2010 App Icon.png|70px|left]] Maya is a popular, [[node]]-based 3D software suite, evolved from [[Wavefront Technologies|Wavefront]] Explorer and [[Alias Systems Corporation|Alias]] [[PowerAnimator]] using technologies from both. The software used to be released in two versions: Maya Complete and Maya Unlimited; but is now sold as one software.

Maya was originally released for the [[IRIX]] operating system, and subsequently ported to the [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Linux]], and [[Mac OS X]] operating systems. IRIX support was discontinued after the release of version 6.5. When Autodesk acquired Alias in October 2005, they continued Maya development. The latest version, 2011 (12.0), was released in April 2010.

An important feature of Maya is its openness to third-party software, which can strip the software completely of its standard appearance and, using only the [[Geometric modeling kernel|kernel]], transform it into a highly customized version of the software. This feature in itself made Maya appealing to large studios, which tend to write custom code for their productions using the provided [[software development kit]].

A [[Tcl]]-like cross-platform scripting language called ''[[Maya Embedded Language]]'' (''MEL'') is provided not only as a scripting language, but as means to customize Maya's core functionality (much of the environment, commands, and tools are written in the language).  Additionally, user interactions are implemented and recorded as MEL scripting code which users can store on a custom [[toolbar]], allowing animators to add functionality without experience in [[C (programming language)|C]] or [[C++]], though that option is provided with the software development kit. Support for [[Python (programming language)|Python]] scripting was added in version 8.5.

The core of Maya itself is written in [[C++]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.research.att.com/~bs/applications.html List of C++ applications], maintained by C++ creator [[Bjarne Stroustrup]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to standard Maya Binary (.mb extension) scenes, project files can be stored as sequences of MEL operations saved as a human-readable file (.ma, for &quot;Maya [[ASCII]]&quot;). Containing all geometry and animation data, these files are editable in any text editor outside of the Maya environment, thus allowing for a high level of flexibility when working with external tools.

A [[pie menu|marking menu]] is built into larger menu system called Hotbox that provides instant access to a majority of features in Maya at the press of a key.

==Modeling==
[[File:Airbus A300 CGI.jpg|thumb|An example render of a Maya scene.]]
[[Nonuniform rational B-spline|NURBS]], [[Polygon (computer graphics)|polygons]] and [[subdivision surface]]s (or SubDivs or SubD's) are available in Maya.

Polygons are a widely used model medium due to its relative stability and functionality. Polygons are also the visualization bridge between NURBS and SubDivs. NURBS are used for their ready-smooth appearance and respond well to deformations in the Dynamics Workbench.  SubDivs resemble a combination of both NURBS and polygons, but they are actually just a smoothed mesh.&lt;ref&gt;Pisca, Nicholas. ''YSYT - Maya MEL Basics for Designers'', pp 53-54. 0001d Publishing. 2009&lt;/ref&gt; They are ready-smooth and can be manipulated like polygons, resulting in a model of many objects including hands, faces, and other multi-topological constructions. Maya hair tools cannot be applied to subdivision polygons without previous conversion.

==Dynamics and simulation==
Maya features a [[particle system]] for handling masses like steam and water drops. Dynamic fields allow adding gravity, wind and vortexes, allowing for effects such as blowing leaves or even tornadoes. Special tools give artists the ability to brush and style particles like hair and fur. This module is a direct evolution of [[Wavefront Technologies|Wavefront]] [[Dynamation (software)|Dynamation]].

An artist may create [[rigid body]] geometric objects which collide automatically without explicit animation, as well as [[soft body]] objects which can ripple and bend, like                    flags and cloth.

Maya effects are built-in programs that make it easy for users to create complex animation effects such as smoke, fire and realistic water effects, with many options and attributes for tuning the results.

In version 8.5 a powerful cloth simulator called &quot;nCloth&quot; was added, allowing users to simulate cloth with control over aspects such as self-collision and interpenetration. The cloth objects can be modified to behave as rigid or soft bodies.

In version 2009, &quot;nParticles&quot; were added, offering a new particle simulation system (based around the same system running 'nCloth'), in addition to the original particle system available in Maya.  This addition was similar to the inclusion of &quot;nCloth&quot; alongside &quot;Maya Cloth&quot;, insofar as it did not take the place of any existing dynamic tools, despite being newer. (see 'Unlimited Features' below).

==Maya software==
Maya now comes in one version (replacing Maya Unlimited).  Maya Complete has been discontinued.  The new Maya contains all the features of Maya Unlimited 2009&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://usa.autodesk.com/adsk/servlet/pc/compare/index?siteID=123112&amp;id=13583751 |title=Autodesk Maya Features - Compare}}&lt;/ref&gt;:
;Maya Fluid Effects
:A realistic fluid simulator (effective for smoke, fire, clouds and explosions, added in Maya 4.5)
;Maya Classic Cloth
:Cloth simulation to automatically simulate clothing and fabrics moving realistically over an animated character. The Maya Cloth toolset has been upgraded in every version of Maya released after Spider-Man 2. Alias worked with Sony Pictures Imageworks to get Maya Cloth up to scratch for that production, and all those changes have been implemented, although the big studios opted to use third party plugins such as [[Syflex]] instead of the (relatively) cumbersome Maya Cloth.
;Maya Fur
:Animal fur simulation similar to Maya Hair. It can be used to simulate other fur-like objects, such as grass.
;Maya Hair
:A simulator for realistic-looking human hair implemented using curves and Paint Effects. These are also known as dynamic curves.
;Maya Live
:A set of motion tracking tools for CG matching to clean plate footage.
;Maya nCloth
:Added in version 8.5, nCloth is the first implementation of Maya Nucleus, Autodesk's simulation framework. nCloth gives the artist further control of cloth and material simulations.
;Maya nParticle
:Added in version 2009, nParticle is addendum to Maya Nucleus toolset. nParticle is for simulating a wide range of complex 3D effects, including liquids, clouds, smoke, spray, and dust.
;MatchMover
:Added to Maya 2010, this enables compositing of CGI elements with motion data from video and film sequences.
;Maya Composite
:Added to Maya 2010,this was earlier sold as [[Toxik]].
;Camera Sequencer: 
:Added after Maya unlimited 2009, Camera Sequencer is used to layout multiple camera shots and manage them in one animation sequence. 
==Scripting and plugins==
In Maya, all attributes are parametric, meaning anything can be connected to anything (e.g. a color intensity of a shader can be used to control the movement of a door opening and closing). To control the node-based system of Maya, its fully reconfigurable user interface can be scripted with [[Maya Embedded Language|MEL]] script code which can be dropped onto a shelf to create a new icon that executes that code.

With the release of Maya 8.5 support for the [[Python (programming language)|Python scripting language]] has been included. The current implementation of Python in Maya is not fully object oriented though.
*[[List of Maya plugins]]

===MEL scripting===
Maya has an embedded script language called MEL, [[Maya Embedded Language]], which is similar to TCL and Perl programming. Code written in MEL can be executed from the script editor, shelves, and drop down menus.

MEL affords more access and control than what was designed in the User Interface; some functions of the software and advanced options are only available by using MEL programming.
All Maya preferences, commands, toolbars, and drop down menus are MEL code. By recording from the Script Editor History Window or scanning the Maya Program Files directory, it is possible to retrieve the original MEL procedures and functions.

MEL is not object oriented, so it is impossible to create custom classes and methods as you would in C++ or Python.
The advantage of this is that it gives MEL a strong structure making it accessible and easier to understand to Maya users and to first time programmers.
Also the linear scripting nature of the language would assist the user in making the most of the Maya nodes instead of tempting him/her to make their own objects, as in case of object oriented languages.

==Learning tools==
Along with the history of Maya the company has produced Maya learning tools which date back to the earlier Alias days. Beginning with an internally produced newsletter on Maya software techniques and workflows, the company continued with the internally produced Art of Maya book and training videos and tutorials. In response to strong user demand the company's education department further developed instructional books and video-based learning content referred to as learning tools. Autodesk continues to develop learning tools with content developed both by internal product specialists as well as industry professionals. The company's video-based learning tools have recently moved away from physical production and are now available as digital downloads.{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}}

==Use in films==
Many popular computer-animated films have been made with Maya software, including ''[[Resident Evil: Degeneration]]'', ''[[Ice Age (film series)|Ice Age]]'', its sequel ''[[Ice Age: The Meltdown]]'', ''[[Geng: The Adventure Begins]]'', ''[[Monsters vs. Aliens]]'', ''[[Avatar (2009 film)|Avatar]]'', and others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://images.autodesk.com/adsk/files/dreamworks_animation_skg_customer_story.pdf |title=Dreamworks SKG and Maya}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[3D computer graphics]]
* [[3D computer graphics software]]
* [[Alias Systems Corporation]]
* [[Autodesk]]
* [[Autodesk Media and Entertainment]]
* [[Autodesk 3ds Max]]
* [[Autodesk Softimage]]
* [[Indigo Renderer]] - A third-party photorealistic renderer with plugins for maya.
* [[Silicon Graphics, Inc.]]
* [[Wavefront Technologies]]
* [[Zebra striping]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
*&quot;Maya 7 for Windows and Macintosh&quot; by Danny Riddel, Morgan Robinson and Nathaniel Stein. Peachpit Press, 2006.
*&quot;Mel Scripting for Maya Animators&quot; by Mark R. Wilkins and Chris Kazmier, Morgan Kaufmann Publishers, 2005.
*&quot;Understanding Maya&quot; by Sergey Tsiptsin, ArtHouse Media, 2007.
*&quot;YSYT - Maya MEL Basics for Designers&quot; By Nicholas Pisca, 0001d Publishing, 2009.  ISBN 978-0-578-00988-9
*&quot;Maya startup windows&quot; http://www.toxik.sk/maya-startup-window-history

==External links==
&lt;!--
     Please keep links relevant, ie sites that relate primarily to Maya, not general 3d sites.
     Also note comment below on commercial links being disallowed.
--&gt;
* [http://www.autodesk.com/maya Maya product page]
* [http://area.autodesk.com/ Community Autodesk]
* [http://www.alias.com/glb/eng/press/press_release_details.jsp?itemId=3600004 Autodesk Signs Definitive Agreement to Acquire Alias.]
* [http://www.autodesk.com/autodeskandalias Autodesk Completes Acquisition of Alias]
&lt;!--
     Do not place advertisements here.
     COMMERCIAL LINKS WILL BE REMOVED.
     See WP:EL, and WP:SPAM for more information.
     If you think that your link might be useful, instead of placing it here, put
     it on this article's discussion page first.
     Wikipedia is not a link directory.  Consider submitting your link to DMOZ instead.
--&gt;
{{Animation editors}}
{{3D software}}

[[Category:Autodesk]]
[[Category:3D graphics software]]
[[Category:Computer-aided design software]]
[[Category:Animation software]]
[[Category:Software that uses Qt]]
[[Category:IRIX software]]

[[ar:مايا (برمجيات)]]
[[cs:Maya (software)]]
[[de:Maya (Software)]]
[[es:Autodesk Maya]]
[[fa:نرم‌افزار مایا]]
[[fr:Maya (logiciel)]]
[[ko:마야 (소프트웨어)]]
[[id:Maya (perangkat lunak)]]
[[it:Autodesk Maya]]
[[he:Maya]]
[[lv:Maya (programmatūra)]]
[[lt:Maya]]
[[hu:Maya (program)]]
[[ml:ഓട്ടോഡെസ്ക് മായ]]
[[nl:Maya (software)]]
[[ja:Maya]]
[[no:Maya (programvare)]]
[[pl:Maya (program komputerowy)]]
[[pt:Maya (software)]]
[[ro:Maya (software)]]
[[ru:Maya]]
[[si:මායා (මෘදුකාංගය)]]
[[simple:Maya (software)]]
[[fi:Maya (tietokoneohjelma)]]
[[sv:Maya (datorprogram)]]
[[te:మాయా]]
[[tr:Autodesk Maya]]
[[zh:Maya]]</text>
    </revision>
  </page>
</file>
